<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Collier’s Weekly, vol. 21, no. 1: a digital edition</title>
            <title type="sub">The Turn of the Screw (1898)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>Taylor edition</date>
            </edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp> Edited by </resp>
               <persName>1078975<lb/>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>5 pages transcribed, 24 images.<note>Partial</note></extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Taylor Institution Library, one of the Bodleian Libraries of the University of Oxford, </publisher> <date>2024. </date>
            <availability>
               <licence xml:id="xml_files" target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> XML files are available for download under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</ref>
                  <graphic url="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/4.0/80x15.png"/>. </licence> <licence xml:id="image_files"> Images are reproduced from the Internet Archive.</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="Internet-Archive">https://archive.org/details/sim_colliers-the-national-weekly_1898-04-09_21_1/</idno>
            <idno type="ISSN">2161-6477</idno>
            <idno type="Git">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/1078975/Turn-of-the-Screw/main/Collier's%20Encoding/Colliers-vol21no1.xml</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:id="tayeditions">Taylor Editions: </title>
            <title xml:id="guest">Guest</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="images">PNG</note>
            <note type="holding"><p>Transcribed from: <orgName>Internet Archive</orgName>: pages 18–22. </p></note>
            <note type="intro">
               <p>This is a facsimile and transcription of <title>Collier’s Weekly: An Illustrated Journal of Art, Literature &amp; Current Events, vol. 21, no. 1</title>. </p>
               <p>The transcription was encoded in TEI P5 XML by 1078975. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title ref="#https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1109549">Collier’s Weekly: An Illustrated Journal of Art, Literature &amp; Current Events.</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="#https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7345851">Robert J. Collier</persName>.
                  </editor>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>
                     <persName ref="#https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7173900">Peter F. Collier</persName>
                  </publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York: </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1898-04-09">April 09, 1898</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by transcribing and encoding from Internet Archive scans of microfilm of the periodical, which measures 10 x 15 inches. </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This is a digital edition of <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title>, vol. 21, no. 1, which was created as part of a master's dissertation project entitled <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> (1898).</p>
            <p><title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> was first published serially in twelve weekly installments in the magazine <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title>. This digital edition of <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title> contains the eleventh installment of the novel. The pages containing <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> by Henry James have been transcribed in full. Because of a desire to respect the text-of-the-document, the transcription preserves spelling mistakes, inconsistencies in punctuation, and other errors that might typically be silently corrected. While the other pages of the magazine have not been transcribed, their facsimiles have been included in this edition to encourage study of the periodical codes of the novel. Because users can reference facsimiles, various formatting and forme work have not been encoded. Basic textual rendition has been encoded apart from decorative initial captials and small capitals marking the beginning of sections, which are better represented by the facsimile images. Illustrations have been encoded to encourage users to reference the page facsimiles. Users are also encouraged to consult the other Taylor Editions of <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title> and <title rend="italic">The Two Magics</title>, where <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> was first published in book form later in 1898.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change resp="#1078975"><date>2024-07-01</date>Encoding completed.</change>
         <change resp="#EH">
            <date>2021-03</date>
            <label>template created</label></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="Colliers-vol21no1">
     <front>
        <pb n="1" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-1"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
     </front>
     <body>
        <pb n="2" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-2"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="3" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-3"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="4" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-4"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="5" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-5"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="6" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-6"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="7" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-7"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="8" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-8"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="9" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-9"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="10" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-10"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="11" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-11"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="12" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-12"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="13" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-13"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="14" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-14"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="15" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-15"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="16" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-16"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="17" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-17"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="18" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-18"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>An illustration adjacent to the left margin of the page. The image shows three women standing in a wooded area. One plays a instrument. This illustration is consistent with the Easter theme of the issue.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <head rend="caps center">The Turn of the Screw</head>
            <byline rend="caps center">By Henry James</byline>
            <div type="chapter" n="21">
               <head rend="center">XXI</head>
               <p rend="indent">Before a new day, in my room, had fully broken, my eyes opened to Mrs. Grose, who had come to my bedside with worse news. Flora was so markedly feverish that an illness was perhaps at hand; she had passed a night of extreme unrest, a night agitated above all by fears that had for theiwr subject not in the least her former, but wholly her present governess. It was not against the possible re-entrance of Miss Jessel on the scene that she protested—it was conspicuously and passionately against mine. I was promptly on my feet of course, and with an immense deal to ask; the more that my friend had discernibly now girded her loins to meet me once more. This I felt as soon as I had put to her the question of her sense of the child’s sincerity as against my own. “She persists in denying to you that she saw, or has ever seen, anything?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">My visitor’s trouble, truly, was great. “Ah, Miss, it isn’t a matter on which I can push her! Yet it isn’t either, I must say, as if I much needed to. It has made her, every inch of her, quite old.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Oh, I see her perfectly from here. She resents, for all the world like some high little personage, the imputation on her truthfulness, and, as it were, her respectability. ‘Miss Jessel indeed—<emph rend="italic">she!</emph>’ Ah, she’s ‘respectable,’ the chit! The impression she gave me there yesterday was, I assure you, the very strangest of all; it was quite beyond any of the others. I <emph rend="italic">did</emph> put my foot in it! She’ll never speak to me again.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">Hideous and obscure as it all was, it held Mrs. Grose briefly silent; then she granted my point with a frankness which, I made sure, had more behind it. “I think indeed Miss, she never will. She do have a grand manner about it!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“And that manner”—I summed it up—“is practically what’s the matter with her now.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">Oh, that manner, I could see in my visitor’s face, and not a little else besides! “She asks me every three minutes if I think you’re coming in.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“I see—I see.” I too, on my side, had so much more than worked it out. “Has she said to you since yesterday—except to repudiate her familiarity with anything so dreadful—a single other word about Miss Jessel?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Not one, Miss. And of course you know,” my friend added, “I took it from her, by the lake, that, just then and there at least, there <emph rend="italic">was</emph> nobody.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Rather! And, naturally, you take it from her still.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“I don’t contradict her. What else can I do?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Nothing in the wide world! You’ve the cleverest little person to deal with. They’ve made them—their two friends, I mean—still cleverer, even, than nature did; for it was wondrous material to play on! Flora has now her grievance, and she’ll work it to the end.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Yes, Miss; but to <emph rend="italic">what</emph> end?</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Why, that of dealing with me to her uncle. She’ll make me out to him the lowest creature—!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I winced at the fair show of the scene in Mrs. Grose’s face; she looked for a minute as if she sharply saw them together. “And him who thinks so well of you!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“He has an odd way—it comes over me now,” I laughed—“of proving it! But that doesn’t matter. What Flora wants, of course, is to get rid of me.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">My companion bravely concurred. “Never again to so much as look at you.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“So that what you’ve come to me now for,” I asked, “is to speed me on my way?” Before she had time to reply, however, I had her in check. “I’ve a better idea—the result of my reflections. My going <emph rend="italic">would</emph> seem the right thing, and on Sunday I was terribly near it. Yet that won’t do. It’s <emph rend="italic">you</emph> who must go. You must take Flora.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">My visitor, at this, did speculate. “But where on earth—?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Away from here. Away from <emph rend="italic">them</emph>. Away, even most of all, now, from <emph rend="italic">me</emph>. Straight to her uncle.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Only to tell on you—?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“No, not ‘only’! To leave me, in addition, with my remedy.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">She was still vague. “And what <emph rend="italic">is</emph> your remedy?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Your loyalty, to begin with. And then Miles’s.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">She looked at me hard. Do you think <emph rend="italic">he—?</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Won’t, if he has the chance, turn on me? Yes, I venture still to think it. At all events, I want to try. Get off with his sister as soon as possible and leave me with him alone.” I was amazed, myself, at the spirit I had still in reserve, and therefore perhaps a trifle the more disconcerted at the way in which, in spite of this fine example of it, she hesitated. “There’s one thing, of course,” I went on: “they mustn’t, before she goes, see each other for three seconds.” Then it came over me that, in spite of Flora’s presumable sequestration from the instant of her return from the pool, it might already be too late. “Do you mean,” I anxiously asked, “that they <emph rend="italic">have</emph> met?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">At this she quite flushed. “Ah, Miss, I’m not such a fool as that! If I’ve been obliged to leave her three or four times, it has been each time with one of the maids, and at present, though she’s alone, she’s locked in safe. And yet—and yet!” There were too many things.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“And yet what?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Well, are you so sure of the little gentleman?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“I’m not sure of anything but <emph rend="italic">you</emph>. But I have, since last evening, a new hope. I think he wants to give me an opening. I do believe that—poor little exquisite wretch!—he wants to speak. Last evening, in the firelight and the silence, he sat with me for two hours as if it were just coming.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">Mrs. Grose looked hard, through the window, at the gray, gathering day. “And did it come?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“No, though I waited and waited, I confess it didn’t, and it was without a breach of the silence or so much as a faint allusion to his sister’s condition, and the absence that we at last kissed for good-night. All the same,” I continued, “I can’t, if her uncle sees <emph rend="italic">her</emph>, consent to his seeing her brother without my having given the boy—and most of all because things have got so bad—a little more time.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">My friend, on this ground, appeared more reluctant than I could quite understand. “What do you mean by more time?”</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-19"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>An illustration adjacent to the right margin of the page. The image shows two women in a wooded area, who appear to be dancing. This illustration is consistent with the Easter theme of the issue.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p rend="indent">“Well, a day or two—really to bring it out. He’ll then be on <emph rend="italic">my</emph> side—of which you see the importance. If nothing comes, I shall only fail, and you will, at the worst, have helped me by doing, on your arrival in town, whatever you may have found possible.” So I put it before her, but she continued, for a little so inscrutably embarrassed that I came again to her aid. “Unless indeed,” I wound up, “you really want <emph rend="italic">not</emph> to go.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I could see it, in her face, at last clear itself; she put out her hand to me as a pledge. “I’ll go—I’ll go. I’ll go this morning.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I wanted to be very just. “If you <emph rend="italic">should</emph> wish to wait, I would engage she shouldn’t see me.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“No, no: it’s the place itself. She must leave it.” She held me a moment with heavy eyes, then brought out the rest. “Your idea’s the right one. I myself, Miss—”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Well?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“I can’t stay.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">The look she gave me with it made me jump at possibilities.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“You mean that, since yesterday, you <emph rend="italic">have</emph> seen—?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">She shook her head with dignity. “I’ve <emph rend="italic">heard—!</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Heard?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“From that child—horrors! There!” she sighed with tragic relief. “On my honor, Miss, she says things—!” But at this evocation she broke down; she dropped, with a sudden sob, upon my sofa and, as I had seen her do before, gave way to all the grief of it.</p>
               <p rend="indent">It was quite in another manner that I, for my part, let myself go. “Oh, thank God!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">She sprang up again at this, drying her eyes with a groan. “‘Thank God’?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“It justifies me so!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“It does <emph rend="italic">that</emph>, Miss!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I couldn’t have desired more emphasis, but I just hesitated. “She’s so horrible?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I saw my colleague scarce knew how to put it. “Really shocking.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“And about <emph rend="italic">me?</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“About you, Miss—since you <emph rend="italic">must</emph> have it. It’s beyond everything, for a young lady; and I can’t think wherever she must have picked up—</p>
               <p rend="indent">“The appalling language she applies to me? <emph rend="italic">I</emph> can, then!” I broke in with a laugh that was doubtless strange enough.</p>
               <p rend="indent">It only, in truth, left my friend still more grave. “Well, perhaps I ought to also—since I’ve heard some of it before! Yet I can’t bear it,” the poor woman went on, while, with the same movement, she glanced, on my dressing-table, at the face of my watch. “But I must go back.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I kept her, however. “Ah, if you can’t bear it—!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“How can I stop with her?” she asked. “Why, just <emph rend="italic">for</emph> that: to get her away. Far from this,” she pursued, “far from <emph rend="italic">them</emph>—”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“She may be different? she may be free?” I seized her almost with joy. “Then, in spite of yesterday, you <emph rend="italic">believe</emph>—”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“In such doings?” Her simple description of them required, in the light of her expression, to be carried no further, and she gave me the whole thing as she had never done. “I believe.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">Yes, it <emph rend="italic">was</emph> a joy, and we were still shoulder to shoulder: if I might continue sure of that, I should care but little else what happened. My support in the presence of disaster would be the same as it had been in my early need of confidence, and if my friend would answer for my honesty I would answer for all the rest. On the point of taking leave of her, none the less, I was to some extent embarrassed. “There’s one thing of course—it occurs to me—to remember. My letter, giving the alarm, will have reached town before you.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I now perceived still more how she had been beating about the bush and how weary, at last, it had made her. “Your letter won’t have got there. It never went.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“What then became of it?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Goodness knows! Master Miles—”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Do you mean <emph rend="italic">he</emph> took it?” I gasped.</p>
               <p rend="indent">She hung fire, but she presently brought it out. “I mean that I saw yesterday, when I came back with Miss Flora, that it wasn’t where you had put it. Later in the evening I had the chance to question Luke, and he declared that he had neither noticed nor touched it.” We could only exchange, on this, one of our deeper mutual soundings, and it was Mrs. Grose who first brought up the plumb with an almost elate “You see!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Yes, I see that if Miles took it instead he probably will have read and destroyed it.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“And don’t you see anything else?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I faced her a moment with a sad smile. “It strikes me that by this time your eyes are open even wider than mine.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">They proved to be so indeed, but she could still blush, almost, to show it. “I make out now what he must have done at school.” And she gave, in her simple sharpness, and almost droll, disillusioned nod. “He stole!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I turned it over; I tried to be more judicial. “Well—perhaps.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">She looked as if she found me unexpectedly calm. “He stole <emph rend="italic">letters!</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">She couldn’t know my reasons for a calmness after all pretty shallow; so I brought them out as I might. “I hope, then, it was to more purpose than in this case! The note, at any rate, that I put on the table yesterday,” I pursued, “will have given him no scant an advantage—for it contained only the bare demand of his uncle for an interview—that he is already much ashamed of having gone so far for so little, and that what he had on his mind last evening was precisely the need of confession.” I seemed to myself, for the instant, to have mastered it, to see it all. “Leave us, leave us”—I was already at the door hurrying her off. “I’ll get it out of him. If he confesses, he’s saved. And if he’s saved—”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Then <emph rend="italic">you</emph> are?” The dear woman kissed me on this, and I took her farewell. “I’ll save you without him!” she cried as she went.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="22">
               <head rend="center">XXII</head>
               <p rend="indent">Yet it was when she had got off—and I missed her on the spot—that the great pinch really came. If I had counted on what it would give me to find myself alone with Miles I speedily perceived, at least, that it would give me a measure. No hour of my stay, in fact, was so assailed with apprehensions as that of my coming down to learn that the carriage containing Mrs. Grose and my younger pupil had already rolled out of the gates. Now I <emph rend="italic">was</emph>, I said to myself, face to face with the elements, and for much of the rest of the day, while I fought my weakness, I could consider that I had been supremely rash. It was a tighter place still than I had yet turned round in; all the more that, for the first time, I could see in the aspect of others a confused reflection of the crisis. What had happened naturally caused them all to stare; there was too little of the explained, throw out whatever we might, in the suddenness of my colleague’s act. The maids and the men
                  <pb n="20" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-20"/>
                  <floatingText type="images">
                  <body>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>A halftone image of a painting of a woman standing against a background of trees looking toward the upper-right corner of the image.</figDesc>
                     <ab rend="italic" type="copyright">Copyright, 1897, by Douglas Volk</ab>
                     <byline rend="caps">Douglas Volk</byline>
                     <bibl rend="italic" type="title">The Song of the Pines</bibl>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>A halftone image of a portrait of a woman sitting in a chair leaning to the her left with her right arm extended to the right.</figDesc>
                     <byline rend="caps">W.H. Hyde</byline>
                     <bibl rend="italic" type="title">Portrait of Miss Alice Duer</bibl>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="21" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-21"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>A halftone image of a painting of five children catching minnows with nets. Three are to the left of the image in the foreground. Two are to the right of the image in the background.</figDesc>
                     <byline rend="caps">Charles C. Curran</byline>
                     <bibl rend="italic" type="title">Catching Minnows</bibl>
                  </figure>
                  <ab type="head" rend="caps center">Spring Exhibitions at the Academy of Design and Society of American Artists</ab>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>A halftone image of a painting of a herd of cows moving left to right across the painting. A herding dog in the foreground runs alongside and looks up at them.</figDesc>
                     <byline rend="caps">James M. Hart</byline>
                     <bibl rend="italic" type="title">An Old-Time Drove</bibl>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>A halftone image of a painting of six soliders. One, with a bandage around his head approaches a desk, where another is sitting at a desk writing. Four stand behind the seated man.</figDesc>
                     <byline rend="caps">Gilbert Gaul</byline>
                     <bibl rend="italic" type="title">News From the Front</bibl>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>A halftone image of a painting two nude women. One is to the left in the painting and is holding the reins to two horses while she climbs upon a cart. The other helps her.</figDesc>
                     <byline rend="caps">Robert Reid</byline>
                     <bibl rend="italic" type="title">Dawn</bibl>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>A halftone image of a painting of three nude women on a rock in the ocean. One is standing with her arms raised and looking out toward a ship.</figDesc>
                     <byline rend="caps">Herbert Denman</byline>
                     <bibl rend="italic" type="title">Sirens</bibl>
                  </figure>
                  <ab type="head" rend="caps center">Spring Exhibitions at the Academy of Design and Society of American Artists</ab></body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="22" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-22"/>
                  looked blank; the effect of which on my nerves was an aggravation until I saw the necessity of making it a positive aid. It was precisely, in short, by just clutching the helm that I avoided total wreck; and I dare say that, to bear up at all, I became, that morning, very grand and very dry. I welcomed the consciousness that I was charged with much to do, and I caused it to be known as well that, left thus to myself, I was quite remarkably firm. I wandered with that manner, for the next hour or two, all over the place and looked, I have no doubt, as if I were ready for any onset. So, for the benefit of whom it might concern, I paraded with a sick heart.</p>
               <p rend="indent">The person it appeared least to concern proved to be, till dinner, little Miles himself. My perambulations had given me, meanwhile, no glimpse of him, but they had tended to make more public the change that taking place in our relation as a result of his having at the piano, the day before, kept me, in Flora’s interest, so beguiled and befooled. The stamp of publicity had of course been fully given by her confinement and departure, and the change itself was now ushered in by our non-observance of the regular custom of the schoolroom. He had already disappeared when, on my way down, I pushed open his door, and I learned below that he breakfasted—in the presence of a couple of the maids—with Mrs. Grose and his sister. He had then gone out, as he said, for a stroll; than which nothing, I reflected could better have expressed his frank view of the abrupt transformation of my office. What he would now permit this office to consist of was yet to be settled: there was a queer relief, at all events—I mean for myself in especial—in the renouncement of one pretension. If so much had sprung to the surface I scarce put it too strongly in saying that what had perhaps sprung highest was the absurdity of our prolonging the fiction that I had anything more to teach him. It sufficiently stuck out that, by tacit little tricks in which even more than myself he carried out the care for my dignity, I had had to appeal to him to let me off straining to meet him on the ground of his true capacity. He had at any rate his freedom now; I was never to touch it again; as I had amply shown, moreover, when, on his joining me in the schoolroom the previous night, I had uttered, on the subject of the interval just concluded, neither challenge nor hint. I had too much, from this moment, my other ideas. Yet when he at last arrived for our main repast the difficulty of applying them, the accumulations of my problem, were brought straight home to me by the beautiful little presence on which what had occurred had, as yet, for the eye, dropped neither stain nor shadow.</p>
               <p rend="indent">To mark, for the house, the high state I now cultivated I decreed that my meals with the boy should be served, as we called it, downstairs; so that I had been awaiting him in the ponderous pomp of the room outside of the window of which I had had from Mrs. Grose, that first scared Sunday, my flash of something it would scarce have done to call light. Here at present I felt afresh—for I had felt it again and again—how my equilibrium depended on the success of my rigid will, the will to shut my eyes as tight as possible to the truth that what I had to deal with was, revoltingly, against nature. I could only get on at all by taking “nature” into my confidence and my account, by treating my monstrous ordeal as a push in a direction unusual, of course, and unpleasant, but demanding, after all, for a fair front, only another turn of the screw of ordinary human virtue. No attempt, none the less, could well require more tact than just this attempt to supply, one’s self, <emph rend="italic">all</emph> the nature. How could I put even a little of that article into a suppression of reference to what had occurred? How, on the other hand, could I make a reference without a new plunge into the hideous obscure? Well, a sort of answer, after a time, had come to me, and it was so far confirmed as that I was met, incontestably, by the quickened vision of what was rare in my little companion. It was indeed as if he had found even now—as he had so often found at lessons—still some other delicate way to ease me off. Wasn’t there light in the fact which, as we shared our solitude, broke out with a specious glitter it had never yet quite worn?—the fact that (opportunity aiding, precious opportunity which had now come,) it would be preposterous, with a child so endowed, to forego the help one might wrest from absolute intelligence? What had his intelligence been given him for but to save him? Mightn’t one, to reach his mind, risk the stretch of a rude long arm over his character? It was as if, when we were face to face in the dining-room, he had literally shown me the way. The roast mutton was on the table, and I had dispensed with attendance. Miles, before he sat down, stood a moment with his hands in his pockets and looked at the joint, on which he seemed on the point of passing some humorous judgement. But what he presently brought out was: “I say, my dear, is she really very awfully ill?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Little Flora? Not so bad but that she will presently be better. London will set her up. Bly had ceased to agree with her. Come here and take your mutton.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He promptly obeyed me, carried the plate carefully to his seat, and when he was established went on: “Did Bly disagree with her so terribly suddenly?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Not so suddenly as you might think, one had seen it coming on.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Then why didn’t you get her off before?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Before what?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Before she became too ill to travel.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I found myself prompt. “She’s <emph rend="italic">not</emph> too ill to travel: she only might have become so if she had stayed. This was just the moment to seize. The journey will dissipate the influence”—oh, I was grand!—“and carry it off.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“I see, I see”—Miles, for that matter, was grand too. He settled to his repast with the charming little “table manner” that, from the day of his arrival, had relieved me of all grossness of admonition. Whatever he had been driven from school for, it was not for ugly feeding. He was irreproachable, as always, to-day; but he was unmistakably more conscious. He was discernibly trying to take for granted more things than he found, without assistance, quite easy; and he dropped into peaceful silence while he felt his situation. Our meal was of the briefest and mine a vain pretense, and I had the things immediately removed. While this was done Miles stood again with his hands in his little pockets and his back to me—stood and looked out of the wide window through which, that other day, I had seen what pulled me up. We continued silent while the maid was with us—as silent, it whimsically occurred to me, as some young couple who, on their wedding-journey, at the inn, feel shy in the presence of the waiter. He turned round only when the maid had left us. “Well—so we’re alone!”</p>
            </div>
            <trailer><hi rend="center italic">(Concluded next week.)</hi></trailer>
         </div>
        <div type="short-story">
           <head rend="caps center">An Easter Fantasy</head>
           <p>He stood by the open window in the fragrant darkness of the Southern night. The garden below was quiet in the moonlight. The scent of the roses was borne upward to him on the warm night wind. Dimly he could see the tall white liies swaying on their slender stalks. They seemed to beckon to him...He turned from the window, went down the stairs, and out into the garden.</p>
           <p rend="indent">The light breeze stirred among the flowers. It sounded like the faint rustle of a woman's garments. Some sweet peas were growing in a hedge at his side, their delicate flower-wings fluttering as though longing to take flight. As he turned idly to pluck one, he saw, standing beside him, the girl who had dominated his boyhood’s dreams.</p>
           <p rend="indent">Softly the moonlight played over her bright hair; the freshness of youth lay upon her as the dew upon the flowers.</p>
           <p rend="indent">“I am the essence of the Sweet Pea, and of the Springtime of Youth and Love,” she breathed softly. “Come to me, and they shall be yours again. Think not that the joys of knowledge are sweeter.”</p>
           <p rend="indent">For a minute, as she spoke, it seemed to the man that he caught a breath of half-forgotten fragrance of that golden age, with its winged hopes, its opalescent dreams. He moved impetuously toward her, the old leap at his heart again, treading carelessly upon the mignonette growing in the border of the path. The faint perfume of it floated up to him, and the words that he would have spoken faded from his mind; for he saw another woman standing before him. Her hair was red
           <floatingText type="advertisement" rend="hyphenBefore">
              <body>
                 <head rend="center">Pears’</head>
                 <p rend="indent">Whoever wants soft hands, smooth hands, white hands, or a clear complexion, he and she can have both: that is, if the skin is naturally transparent; unless occupation prevents.</p>
                 <p rend="indent">The color you want to avoid comes probably neither of nature or work, but of habit.</p>
                 <p rend="indent">Either you do not wash effectually, or you wash too effectually; you do not get the skin open and clean, or you hurt it.</p>
                 <p rend="indent">Rememdy—Use Pears’ Soap, no matter how much; but a little is enough if you use it often.</p>
                 <p rend="indent">All sorts of stores sell it, especially druggists; all sorts of people use it.</p>
              </body>
           </floatingText>
        <pb n="23" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-23"/>
              <gap extent="10" unit="line" reason="editorial"/>
              <gap extent="11" unit="paragraph" reason="editorial"/>
           </p>
        </div>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="24" facs="Colliers-vol21no1-24"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
