<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Collier’s Weekly, vol. 20, no. 19: a digital edition (The Turn of the Screw in America, 1898)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>Taylor edition</date>
            </edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp> Edited by </resp>
               <persName>1078975<lb/>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>3 pages transcribed, 24 images.<note>Partial</note></extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Taylor Institution Library, one of the Bodleian Libraries of the University of Oxford, </publisher> <date>2024. </date>
            <availability>
               <licence xml:id="xml_files" target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> XML files are available for download under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</ref>
                  <graphic url="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/4.0/80x15.png"/>. </licence> <licence xml:id="image_files"> Images are reproduced from the Internet Archive.</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="Internet-Archive">https://archive.org/details/sim_colliers-the-national-weekly_1898-02-12_20_19/</idno>
            <idno type="ISSN">2161-6477</idno>
            <idno type="Git">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/1078975/Turn-of-the-Screw/main/Collier's%20Encoding/Colliers-vol20no19.xml</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:id="tayeditions">Taylor Editions: </title>
            <title xml:id="guest">Guest</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="images">PNG</note>
            <note type="holding"><p>Transcribed from: <orgName>Internet Archive</orgName>: pages 20–22. </p></note>
            <note type="intro">
               <p>This is a facsimile and transcription of <title>Collier’s Weekly: An Illustrated Journal of Art, Literature &amp; Current Events, vol. 20, no. 19</title>. </p>
               <p>The transcription was encoded in TEI P5 XML by 1078975. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title ref="#https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1109549">Collier’s Weekly: An Illustrated Journal of Art, Literature &amp; Current Events.</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="#https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7345851">Robert J. Collier</persName>.
                  </editor>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>
                     <persName ref="#https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7173900">Peter F. Collier</persName>.
                  </publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York: </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1898-02-12">February 12, 1898</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
               <p>Created by transcribing and encoding from Internet Archive scans of microfilm of the periodical, which measures 10 x 15 inches. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
               <p>This is a digital edition of <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title>, vol. 20, no. 19, which was created as part of a master's dissertation project entitled <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> in America, 1898.</p>
               <p><title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> was first published serially in twelve weekly installments in the magazine <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title>. This digital edition of <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title> contains the third installment of the novel. The pages containing <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> by Henry James have been transcribed in full. Because of a desire to respect the text-of-the-document, the transcription preserves spelling mistakes, inconsistencies in punctuation, and other errors that might typically be silently corrected. While the other pages of the magazine have not been transcribed, their facsimiles have been included in this edition to encourage study of the periodical codes of the novel. Because users can reference facsimiles, various formatting and forme work have not been encoded. Basic textual rendition has been encoded apart from decorative initial captials and small capitals marking the beginning of sections, which are better represented by the facsimile images. Illustrations have been encoded to encourage users to reference the page facsimiles. Users are also encouraged to consult the other Taylor Editions of <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title> and <title rend="italic">The Two Magics</title>, where <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> was first published in book form later in 1898. These editions have also been uploaded to the <ref target="https://www.prisms.digital/">PRISMS</ref> open scholarship platform, where users may use the workbench tools to consult, compare, and annotate them.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change resp="#1078975"><date>2024-07-01</date>Encoding completed.</change>
         <change resp="#EH">
            <date>2021-03</date>
            <label>template created</label></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="Colliers-vol20no19">
     <front>
        <pb n="1" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-1"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
     </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="2" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-2"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="3" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-3"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="4" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-4"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="5" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-5"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="6" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-6"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="7" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-7"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="8" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-8"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="9" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-9"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="10" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-10"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="11" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-11"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="12" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-12"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="13" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-13"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="14" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-14"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="15" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-15"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="16" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-16"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="17" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-17"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="18" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-18"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="19" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-19"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <div type="installment">
         <pb n="20" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-20"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>The 3 1/2 x 8 1/2 inch masthead illustration of <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title>. In the center panel, the governess turns to face Miles and speak with him. They are surrounded by fog and a large eye appears behind them in the top left of the illustration. In two panels to the left and right of illustration of the governess and Miles, there are illustrations of a dragon-like figure. Below the bottom right of the masthead image, the signature of the illustrator John La Farge, reading “La Farge 98,” appears.</figDesc>
               <byline rend="caps">Drawn by John La Farge</byline>
            </figure>
            <head rend="caps center">The Turn of the Screw</head>
            <byline rend="caps center">By Henry James</byline>
            <div type="chapter" n="3">
               <head rend="center">III</head>
               <p rend="indent">Her thus turning her back on me was fortunately not, for my just preoccupations, a snub that could check the growth of our mutual esteem. We met, after I had brought home little Miles, more intimately than ever on the ground of my stupefaction, my general emotion: so monstrous was I then ready to pronounce it that such a child as had now been revealed to me should be under an interdict. I felt, as he stood wistfully looking out for me (I was a little late on the scene,) before the door of the inn at which the coach had put him down—I felt that I had seen him, on the instant, without and within, in the same great glow of freshness, the same positive fragrance of purity, in which I had, from the first moment, seen his little sister. He was incredibly beautiful, and Mrs. Grose had put her finger on it: everything but a sort of passion of tenderness for him was swept away by his presence. What I then and there took him to my heart for was something divine that I have never found to the same degree in any child—his indescribable little air of knowing nothing in the world but love. It would have been impossible to carry a bad name with a greater sweetness of innocence, and by the time I had got back to Bly with him I remained merely bewildered—so far, that is, as I was not outraged—by the sense of the horrible letter locked up, in my room, in a drawer. As soon as I could compass a private word with Mrs. Grose I declared to her that it was grotesque.</p>
               <p rend="indent">She promptly understood me. “You mean the cruel charge—?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“It doesn’t live an instant. My dear woman, <emph rend="italic">look</emph> at him!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">She smiled at my pretension to have discovered his charm. “I assure you, Miss, I do nothing else! What will you say, then?” she immediately added.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“In answer to the letter?” I had made up my mind. “Nothing.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“And to his uncle?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I was incisive. “Nothing.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“And to the boy himself?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I was wonderful. “Nothing.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">She gave with her apron a great wipe to her mouth. “Then I’ll stand by you. We’ll see it out.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“We’ll see it out!” I ardently echoed, giving her my hand to make it a vow.</p>
               <p rend="indent">She held me there a moment, then whisked up her apron again with her detached hand. “Would you mind, Miss, if I used the freedom—”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“To kiss me? No!” I took the good creature in my arms and, after we had embraced like sisters, felt still more fortified and indignant.</p>
               <p rend="indent">This, at all events, was for the time; a time so full that, as I recall the way it went, reminds me of all the art I now need to make it a little distinct. What I look back at with amazement is the situation I accepted. I had undertaken, with my companion, to see it out, and I was under a charm, apparently, that could smooth away the extent and the far and difficult connections of such an effort. I was lifted aloft on a great wave of infatuation and pity. I found it simple, in my ignorance, my confusion, and perhaps my conceit, to assume that I could deal with a boy whose education for the world was all on the point of beginning. I am unable even to remember at this day what proposal I framed for the end of his holidays and the resumption of his studies. Lessons with me indeed, that charming summer, we all had a theory that he was to have; but I now feel that, for a considerable time, the lessons must have been rather my own. I learned something—at first certainly—that had not been one of the teachings of my old small, smothered life; learned to be amused, and even amusing, and not to think for the morrow. It was the first time, in a manner, that I had known space and air and freedom, all the music of summer and all the mystery of nature. And then there was consideration—and consideration was sweet. Oh, it was a trap—not designed, but deep—to my imagination, to my delicacy, perhaps to my vanity; to whatever, in me, was most excitable. The best way to picture it all is to say that I was off my guard. They gave me so little trouble—they were of a gentleness so extraordinary. I used to speculate—but even this with a dim disconnectedness—as to how the rough future (for all futures are rough!) would handle them and might bruise them. They had the bloom of health and happiness; and yet, as if I had been in charge of a pair of little grandees, of princes of the blood, for whom everything, to be right, would have to be inclosed and protected, the only form that, in my fancy, the after-years could take for them was that of a romantic, a really royal extension of the garden and the park. It may be, of course, above all, that what suddenly broke into this gives the previous time a spell of stillness—that hush in which something gathers or crouches. The change was actually like the spring of a beast.</p>
               <p rend="indent">In the first weeks the days were long; they often, at their finest, gave me what I used to call my own hour, the hour when, for my pupils, tea-time and bed-time having come and gone, I had, before my final retirement, a small interval alone. Much as I liked my companions, this hour was the thing in the day I liked most; and I liked it best of all when, as the light faded—or rather, I should say, the day lingered and the last calls of the last birds sounded, in a flushed sky, from the old trees—I could take a turn in the grounds and enjoy, almost with a sense of property that amused and flattered me, the beauty and dignity of the place. It was a pleasure at these moments to feel myself tranquil and justified; doubtless perhaps also to reflect that by my discretion, my quiet good sense and general high propriety, I was giving pleasure—if he ever thought of it!—to the person to whose pressure I had responded. What I was doing was what he had earnestly hoped and directly asked of me, and that I <emph rend="italic">could</emph>, after all, do it proved even a greater joy than I had expected. I dare say I fancied myself, in short, a remarkable young woman and took comfort in the faith that this would more publicly appear. Well, I needed to be remarkable to offer a front to the remarkable things that presently gave their first sign.</p>
               <p rend="indent">It was plump, one afternoon, in the middle of my very hour: the children were tucked away and I had come out for my stroll. One of the thoughts that, as I don’t in the least shrink now from noting, used to be with me in these wanderings was that it would be as charming as a charming story suddenly to meet some one. Some one would appear there at the turn of a path and would stand before me and smile and approve. I didn’t ask more than that—I only asked that he should <emph rend="italic">know</emph>, and the only way to be sure he knew would be to see it, and the kind light of it, in his handsome face. That was exactly present to me—by which I mean the face was—when, on the first of these occasions, at the end of a long June day, I stopped short on emerging from
         <pb n="21" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-21"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>An 8 1/2 x 12 1/4 inch illustration of the governess reacting to the silhouette atop a tower. Below the bottom left corner of the image, an image of a woman and the signature of the illustrator Eric Pape appear.</figDesc>
                     <ab rend="caps center" type="caption">He did stand there!—but high up, beyond the lawn and at the very top of the tower...</ab>
                  </figure>
         <pb n="22" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-22"/>one of the plantations and coming into view of the house. What arrested me on the spot—and with a shock much greater than any vision had allowed for—was the sense that my imagination had, in a flash, turned real. He did stand there!—but high up, beyond the lawn and at the very top of the tower to which, on that first morning, little Flora had conducted me. This tower was one of a pair—square, incongruous, crenelated structures—that were distinguished, for some reason, though I could see little difference, as the new and the old. They flanked opposite ends of the house and were probably architectural absurdities, redeemed in a measure indeed by not being wholly disengaged nor of a height too pretentious, dating, in their gingerbread antiquity, from a romantic revival that was already a respectable past. I admired them, had fancies about them, for we could all profit in a degree, especially when they loomed through the dusk, by the grandeur of their actual battlements; yet it was not at such an elevation that the figure I had so often invoked seemed most in place.</p>
               <p rend="indent">It produced in me, this figure, in the clear twilight, I remember, two distinct gasps of emotion, which were, sharply, the shocks of my first and of my second surprise. My second was a violent perception of the mistake of my first: the man who met my eyes was not the person I had precipitately supposed. There came to me thus a bewilderment of vision of which, after these years, there is no living view that I can hope to give. An unknown man in a lonely place is a permitted object of fear to a young woman privately bred; and the figure that faced me was—a few more seconds assured me—as little any one else I knew as it was the image that had been in my mind. I had not seen it in Harley Street—I had not seen it anywhere. The place, moreover, in the strangest way in the world, had, on the instant and by the very fact of its appearance, become lonely. To myself at least, making my statement here with a deliberation with which I have never made it, the whole feeling of the moment returns. It was as if, while I took in—what I did take in—all the rest of the scene had been stricken with death. I can hear again, as I write, the intense hush in which the sounds of evening dropped. The rooks stopped cawing in the golden sky and the friendly hour lost, for the minute, all its voice. But there was no other change in nature, unless indeed it were a change that I saw with a stranger sharpness. The gold was still in the sky, the clearness in the air, and the man who looked at me over the battlements was as definite as a picture in a frame. That’s how I thought, with extraordinary quickness, of each person that he might have been and that he was not. We were confronted across our distance quite long enough for me to ask myself with intensity who then he was and to feel, as an effect of my inability to say, a wonder that in a few instants more became intense.</p>
               <p rend="indent">The great question, or one of these, is, afterward, I know, with regard to certain matters, the question of how long they have lasted. Well, this matter of mine, think what you will of it, lasted while I caught at a dozen possibilities, none of which made a difference for the better, that I could see, in there having been in the house—and for how long, above all?—a person of whom I was in ignorance. It lasted while I just bridled a little with the sense that my office demanded that there should be no such ignorance and no such person. It lasted while this visitant, at all events—and there was a touch of the strange freedom, as I remember, in the sign of familiarity of his wearing no hat—seemed to fix me, from his position, with just the question, just the scrutiny through the fading light, that his own presence provoked. We were too far apart to call to each other, but there was a moment at which, at shorter range, some challenge between us, breaking the hush, would have been the right result of our straight mutual stare. He was in one of the angles, the one away from the house, very erect, as it struck me, and with both hands on the ledge. So I saw him as I see the letters I form on this page; then, exactly, after a minute, as if to add to the spectacle, he slowly changed his place—passed, looking at me hard all the while, to the opposite corner of the platform. Yes, I had the sharpest sense that, during this transit, he never took his eyes from me, and I can see at this moment the way his hand, as he went, passed from one of the crenelations to the next. He stopped at the other corner, but less long, and even as he turned away still markedly fixed me. He turned away; that was all I knew.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer><hi rend="center italic">(To be continued.)</hi></trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p rend="indent"><seg type="head" rend="small-caps">Something New.</seg> We have just recieved notice from the Clyde Steamship Company, the only line which operates steamers between New York, Charleston and Jacksonville, Fla., that the Dining Saloon and Staterooms heretofore on the main deck of their steamers Algonquin and Seminole have been removed and this deck given over to freight only, thus making all Staterooms upper deck. The Dining Saloon, which is now also on Promenade Deck, just abaft of ’midships, extends the entire width of the ship, offering passengers a cool, airy room, from which a grand view is always obtainable. Forward and aft of the Dining Saloon are the first-class Staterooms, all cheery, light and well ventilated.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The Social Hall, for first-class passengers, located on the Awning Deck above the Dining Room, is large and airy, furnished with magnificent velvet carpet, and also has piano for use and amusement of passengers. Stepping out of the Social Hall, the passenger finds a fine Promenade Deck the full width of the ship and offering a delightful place for exercise or rest.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Such are some of the comforts to be found by passengers traveling by the Clyde Line, and when we received this advice from their head office, which is located at 5 Bowling Green, New York, we felt it our duty and pleasure to impart this valuable information to our readers, who will undoubtedly receive prompt replies to their communications requesting reservations and literature issued by this popular line between the North and South.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head rend="caps center">Our Fashion Letter</head>
            <opener rend="small-caps">My dear May:</opener>
            <p rend="indent">It is delightful to see the new summer shirtwaists. They make one wish for the sunny warm weather when blouses and skirts will be the order of the day, and furs be discarded. What a wonderful life the shirtwaist has had! Fashions come and go, but the shirtwaist goes on forever.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The new shirtwaists are new in only one sense. They are made as before, only much better in cut and finish; the English shirts, made with plain yoke, collar and cuffs, are admitted quite the best in this style; they fit close to the figure and are the delight of the “tailor-built” girl. Shirtwaists which are more in the blouse style are literally covered with tucks; some have only tucked yokes and sleeves—such wee tucks they are in most cases; the blouses with broader tucks in rows of threes and fives are charming for long-waisted, slim girls, but most unbecoming to any one inclined to be stout, especially when each tuck has a piping above in a contrasting color. There are shirred yokes and sleeves and bodices trimmed with a frill of embroidery down the left side. Quite a pretty effect and finish to the shirtwaist is a frill slightly fulled on to the belt; it gives a softer appearance than a plain belt of leather, petersham or velvet.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The majority of shirtwaists have detachable collars, white and colored, and all sleeves are decidedly smaller. The Roman striped shirtwaist is the newest, and those in gorgeous plaids are quite the most startling; but in cottons are not so vivid as their predecessors in silk. Checks, both large and small, are seen in black and white and colors, and the plaids in “diamonds” instead of “squares” are a distinct change. There are very few stripes, and their absence from Fashion’s list will make them more desirable. I think the brilliant colorings of the plaids will soon weary the eye; besides, what an abundant supply one would require of them, for anything conspicuous so soon becomes common. The materials include ordinary shirtings, duck, thick gingham, pique, madras, dimity, corded batiste and lawn, and each is delightfully fresh and cool-looking.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The new organdies and printed mulls, which must be made over a color, are the most charmingly effective dainty bodices one can imagine, but of course are not for morning or ordinary wear.</p>
            <p rend="indent">With the arrival of shirtwaists there is naturally a rush for something new in belts, and of all the varieties I think the “miniature” belt is the most beautiful. It is composed of miniatures connected with gilt chains; the clasps of enamel studded with imitation emeralds and garnets. There are many styles in leather belts, narrow and broad, plain and jeweled clasps, and the jewels of the clasp match the colors of the leathers; with red leather the clasps are studded with rubies, with blue they are studded with turquoise, and the tans have topaz. The girdle, which is newer than a belt, is about four inches wide and made of soft silk in plaids and Roman stripes; it should fasten in front with a buckle. A quaint and pretty
            <floatingText type="advertisement">
               <body>
               <head rend="center">Pears’</head>
               <p rend="indent">It is a wonderful soap that takes hold quick and does no harm.</p>
               <p rend="indent">No harm! It leaves the skin soft like a baby’s; no alkali in it, nothing but soap. The harm is done by alkali. Still more harm is done by not washing. So, bad soap is better than none.</p>
                  <p rend="indent">What is bad soap? Imperfectly made; the fat and alkali not well balanced or not combined.</p>
                  <p rend="indent">What is good soap?</p>
                  <p rend="center">Pears’.</p>
                  <p rend="indent">All sorts of stores sell it, especially druggists; all sorts of people use it.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         <pb n="23" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-23"/>
               <gap extent="3" unit="line" reason="editorial"/>
            </p>
            <gap extent="1" unit="paragraph" reason="editorial"/>
         </div>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
         <pb n="24" facs="Colliers-vol20no19-24"/>
         <gap extent="1" unit="page" reason="editorial"/>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
