<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Collier’s Weekly, vol. 21, no. 2: a digital edition (The Turn of the Screw in America, 1898)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>Taylor edition</date>
            </edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp> Edited by </resp>
               <persName>1078975<lb/>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>3 pages transcribed, 24 images.<note>Partial</note></extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Taylor Institution Library, one of the Bodleian Libraries of the University of Oxford, </publisher> <date>2024. </date>
            <availability>
               <licence xml:id="xml_files" target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> XML files are available for download under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</ref>
                  <graphic url="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/4.0/80x15.png"/>. </licence> <licence xml:id="image_files"> Images are reproduced from the Internet Archive.</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="Internet-Archive">https://archive.org/details/sim_colliers-the-national-weekly_1898-04-16_21_2/</idno>
            <idno type="ISSN">2161-6477</idno>
            <idno type="Git">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/1078975/Turn-of-the-Screw/main/Collier's%20Encoding/Colliers-vol21no2.xml</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:id="tayeditions">Taylor Editions: </title>
            <title xml:id="guest">Guest</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="images">PNG</note>
            <note type="holding"><p>Transcribed from: <orgName>Internet Archive</orgName>: pages 16–18. </p></note>
            <note type="intro">
               <p>This is a facsimile and transcription of <title>Collier’s Weekly: An Illustrated Journal of Art, Literature &amp; Current Events, vol. 21, no. 2</title>. </p>
               <p>The transcription was encoded in TEI P5 XML by 1078975. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title ref="#https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1109549">Collier’s Weekly: An Illustrated Journal of Art, Literature &amp; Current Events.</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="#https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7345851">Robert J. Collier</persName>.
                  </editor>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>
                     <persName ref="#https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7173900">Peter F. Collier</persName>.
                  </publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York: </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1898-04-16">April 16, 1898</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by transcribing and encoding from Internet Archive scans of microfilm of the periodical, which measures 10 x 15 inches. </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This is a digital edition of <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title>, vol. 21, no. 2, which was created as part of a master's dissertation project entitled <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> in America, 1898.</p>
            <p><title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> was first published serially in twelve weekly installments in the magazine <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title>. This digital edition of <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title> contains the final installment of the novel. The pages containing <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> by Henry James have been transcribed in full. Because of a desire to respect the text-of-the-document, the transcription preserves spelling mistakes, inconsistencies in punctuation, and other errors that might typically be silently corrected. While the other pages of the magazine have not been transcribed, their facsimiles have been included in this edition to encourage study of the periodical codes of the novel. Because users can reference facsimiles, various formatting and forme work have not been encoded. Basic textual rendition has been encoded apart from decorative initial captials and small capitals marking the beginning of sections, which are better represented by the facsimile images. Illustrations have been encoded to encourage users to reference the page facsimiles. Users are also encouraged to consult the other Taylor Editions of <title rend="italic">Collier’s Weekly</title> and <title rend="italic">The Two Magics</title>, where <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title> was first published in book form later in 1898. These editions have also been uploaded to the <ref target="https://www.prisms.digital/">PRISMS</ref> open scholarship platform, where users may use the workbench tools to consult, compare, and annotate them.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change resp="#1078975"><date>2024-07-01</date>Encoding completed.</change>
         <change resp="#EH">
            <date>2021-03</date>
            <label>template created</label></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="Colliers-vol21no2">
     <front>
        <pb n="1" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-1"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
     </front>
     <body>
        <pb n="2" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-2"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="3" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-3"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="4" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-4"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="5" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-5"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="6" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-6"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="7" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-7"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="8" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-8"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="9" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-9"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="10" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-10"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="11" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-11"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="12" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-12"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="13" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-13"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="14" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-14"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
        <pb n="15" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-15"/>
        <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
         <div type="installment">
            <pb n="16" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-16"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>The 3 1/2 x 8 1/2 inch masthead illustration of <title rend="italic">The Turn of the Screw</title>. In the center panel, the governess turns to face Miles and speak with him. They are surrounded by fog and a large eye appears behind them in the top left of the illustration. In two panels to the left and right of illustration of the governess and Miles, there are illustrations of a dragon-like figure. Below the bottom right of the masthead image, the signature of the illustrator John La Farge, reading “La Farge 98,” appears.</figDesc>
               <byline rend="caps">Drawn by John La Farge</byline>
            </figure>
            <head rend="caps center">The Turn of the Screw</head>
            <byline rend="caps center">By Henry James</byline>
            <div type="chapter" n="23">
               <head rend="center">XXIII</head>
               <p rend="indent">Oh, more or less.” I fancy my smile was pale. “Not absolutely. We shouldn’t like that!” I threw in.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“No—I suppose we shouldn’t. Of course we have the others.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“We have the others—we have indeed the others,” I concurred.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Yet even though we have them,” he returned, still with his hands in his pockets and planted there in front of me, “they don’t much count, do they?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I made the best of it, but I felt wan.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“It depends on what you call ‘much’!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Yes”—with all accommodation—“everything depends!” On this, however, he faced to the window again and presently  reached it with his vague, restless, cogitating step. He remained there a while, his forehead against the glass, in contemplation of the stupid shrubs I knew and the dull things of November. I had always my hypocrisy of “work,” behind which, now, I gained the sofa. Steadying myself with it there as I had repeatedly done at those moments of torment that I have described as the moments of my knowing the children to be given to something from which I was barred, I sufficiently obeyed my habit of being prepared for the worst. But an extraordinary impression dropped on me as I extracted a meaning from the boy’s embarrassed back—none other than the impression that I was not barred now. This inference grew in a few minutes to sharp intensity and seemed bound up with the direct perception that it was positively <emph rend="italic">he</emph> who was. The frames and squares of the great window were a kind of image, for him, of a kind of failure. I felt that I saw him, at any rate, shut in or shut out. He was admirable, but not comfortable: I took it in with a throb of hope. Wasn’t he looking, through the haunted pane, for something he couldn’t see?—and wasn’t it the first time in the whole business that he had known such a lapse? The first, the very first: I found it a splendid portent. It made him anxious, though he watched himself; he had been anxious all day and, even while in his usual sweet little manner he sat at table, had needed all his small strange genius to give it a gloss. When he at last turned round to meet me it was almost as if this genius had succumbed. “Well, I think I’m glad Bly agrees with <emph rend="italic">me!</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“You would certainly seem to have seen, these twenty-four hours, a good deal more of it than for some time before. I hope,” I went on bravely, “that you’ve been enjoying yourself.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Oh yes, I’ve been ever so far; all round about—miles and miles away. I’ve never been so free.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He had really a manner of his own, and I could only try to keep up with him. “Well, do you like it?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He stood there smiling; then at last he put into two words—“Do <emph rend="italic">you?</emph>”—more discrimination than I had ever heard two words contain. Before I had time to deal with that, however, he continued as if with the sense that this was an impertinence to be softened. “Nothing could be more charming than the way you take it, for of course if we’re alone together now it’s you that are alone most. But I hope,” he threw out, “you don’t particularly mind!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Having to do with you?” I asked. “My dear child, how can I help minding? Though I’ve renounced all claim to your company—you’re so beyond me!—I at least greatly enjoy it. What else should I stay on for?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He looked at me more directly, and the expression of his face, graver now, struck me as the most beautiful I had ever seen in it. “You stay on just for <emph rend="italic">that?</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Certainly. I stay on as your friend and from the tremendous interest I take in you till something can be done for you that may be more worth your while. That needn’t surprise you.” My voice trembled so that I felt it impossible to suppress the shake. “Don’t you remember how I told you, when I came and sat on your bed the night of the storm, that there was nothing in the world I wouldn’t do for you?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Yes, yes!” He, on his side, more and more visibly nervous, had a tone to master; but he was so much more successful than I that, laughing out through his gravity, he could pretend we were pleasantly jesting. “Only that, I think, was to get me to do something for <emph rend="italic">you!</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“It was partly to get you to do something,” I conceded; “but, you know, you didn’t do it.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Oh yes,” he said with the brightest superficial eagerness, “you wanted me to tell you something.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“That’s it. Out, straight out. What you have on your mind.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Ah then, is <emph rend="italic">that</emph> what you’ve stayed over for?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He spoke with a gayety through which I could still catch the finest little quaver of resentful passion; but I can’t begin to express the effect upon me of an implication of surrender even so faint. It was as if what I had yearned for had come at last only to astonish me. “Well, yes—I may as well make a clean breast of it. It was precisely for that.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He waited so long that I supposed it for the purpose of repudiating the assumption on which my action had been founded; but what he finally said was: “Do you mean now—here?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“There couldn’t be a better place or time.” He looked round him uneasily, and I had the rare—oh, the queer!—impression of the very first symptom I had seen in him of the approach of immediate fear. It was as if he were suddenly afraid of me—which struck me indeed as perhaps the best thing to make him. Yet in the very pangs of the effort I felt it vain to try sternness, and I heard myself the next instant so gentle as to be almost grotesque. “You want so to go out again?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Awfully!” He smiled at me heroically, and the touching little bravery of it was enhanced by his actually flushing with pain. He had picked up his hat, which he had brought in, and stood twirling it in a way that gave me, even as I was thus just nearly reaching port, a perverse horror of what I was doing. To do it in <emph rend="italic">any</emph> way was an act of violence, for what did it consist of but the obtrusion of the idea of grossness and guilt on a small helpless creature who had been for me a revelation of the possibilities of beautiful intercourse? Wasn’t it base to create for a being so exquisite a mere alien awkwardness? I suppose I now read into our situation a clearness it couldn’t have had at the time, for I seem to see our poor eyes already lighted with some spark of a prevision of the anguish that was to come. So we circled about, with terrors and scruples, like fighters not daring to close. But it was for each other we feared! That kept us a little longer suspended and unbruised. “I’ll tell you everything,” Miles said—“I mean I’ll tell you anything you like. You’ll stay on with me, and we shall both be all right, and I <emph rend="italic">will</emph> tell you—I <emph rend="italic">will</emph>. But not now.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Why not now?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">My insistence turned him from me and kept him once more
               <pb n="17" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-17"/>
               at his window in a silence during which, between us, you might have heard a pin drop. Then he was before me again with the air of a person for whom, outside, some one who had frankly to be reckoned with was waiting. “I have to see Luke.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I had not yet reduced him to quite so vulgar a lie, and I felt proportionately ashamed. But, horrible as it was, his lies made up my truth. I achieved thoughtfully a few loops of my knitting. “Well then, go to Luke, and I’ll wait for what you promise. Only, in return for that, satisfy, before you leave me, one very much smaller request.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He looked as if he felt he had succeeded enough to be able still a little to bargain. “Very much smaller—?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Yes, a mere fraction of the whole. Tell me”—oh, my work preoccupied me, and I was off-hand!—“if, yesterday afternoon, from the table in the hall, you took, you know, my letter.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="24">
               <head rend="center">XXIV</head>
               <p rend="indent">My sense of how he received this suffered for a minute from something that I can describe only as a fierce split of my attention—a stroke that at first, as I sprang straight up, reduced me to the mere blind movement of getting hold of him, drawing him close, and, while I just fell, for support, against the nearest piece of furniture, instinctively keeping him with his back to the window. The appearance was full upon us that I had already had to deal with here: Peter Quint had come into view like a sentinel before a prison. The next thing I saw was that, from outside, he had reached the window, and then I knew that, close to the glass and glaring in through it, he offered once more to the room his white face of damnation. It represents but grossly what took place within me at the sight to say that on the second my decision was made; yet I believe that no woman so overwhelmed ever in so short a time recovered her grasp of the <emph rend="italic">act</emph>. It came to me in the very horror of the immediate presence that the act would be, seeing and facing what I saw and faced, to keep the boy himself unaware. The inspiration—I can call it by no other name—was that I felt how voluntarily, how transcendently I <emph rend="italic">might</emph>. It was like fighting with a demon for a human soul, and when I had fairly so appraised it I saw how the human soul—held out, in the tremor of my hands, at arms-length—had a perfect dew of sweat on a lovely childish forehead. The face that was close to mine was as white as the face against the glass, and out of it presently came a sound, not low nor weak, but as if from much further away, that I drank like a waft of fragrance.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Yes—I took it.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">At this, with a moan of joy, I enfolded, I drew him close; and while I held him to my breast, where I could feel in the sudden fever of his little body the tremendous pulse of his little heart, I kept my eyes on the thing at the window and saw it move and shift its posture. I have likened it to a sentinel, but its slow wheel, for a moment, was rather the prowl of a baffled beast. My present quickened courage, however, was such that, not too much to let it through, I had to shade, as it were, my flame. Meanwhile the glare of the face was again at the window, the scoundrel fixed as if to watch and wait. It was the very confidence that I might now defy him, as well as the positive certitude, by this time, of the child’s unconsciousness, that made me go on. “What did you take it for?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“To see what you said about me.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“You opened the letter?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“I opened it.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">My eyes were now, as I held him off a little again, on Miles’s own face, in which the collapse of mockery showed me how complete was its ravage of uneasiness. What was prodigious was that at last, by my triumph, his sense was sealed and his communication stopped: he knew that he was in presence, but knew not of what, and knew still less that I also was and that I did know. And what did this strain of trouble matter when my eyes went back to the window only to see that the air was clear again and—by my personal triumph—the influence quenched? There was nothing there. I felt that the cause was mine and that I should surely get <emph rend="italic">all</emph>. “And you found nothing!”—I let my elation out.</p>
               <p rend="indent">He gave the most mournful, thoughtful, little melancholy headshake. “Nothing.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Nothing, nothing!” I almost shouted in my joy.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Nothing, nothing,” he sadly repeated.</p>
               <p rend="indent">I kissed his forehead; it was drenched. “So what have you done with it?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“I’ve burned it.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Burned it?” It was now or never. “Is that what you did at school?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">Oh, what this brought up! “At school?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Did you take letters?—or other things?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Other things?” He appeared now to be thinking of something far off and that reached him only through the pressure of his anxiety. Yet it did reach him. “Did I <emph rend="italic">steal?</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I felt myself redden to the roots of my hair as well as wonder if it were more strange to put to a gentleman such a question or to see him take it with allowances that gave the very distance of his fall in the world. “Was it for that you mightn’t go back?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">The only thing he felt was rather a dreary little surprise. “Did you know I mightn’t?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“I know everything.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He gave me at this the longest and strangest look. “Everything?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Everything. Therefore <emph rend="italic">did</emph> you—?” But I couldn’t say it again.</p>
               <p rend="indent">Miles could, very simply. “No. I didn’t steal.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">My face must have shown him I believed him utterly; yet my hands—but it was for pure tenderness—shook him as if to ask why, if it was all for nothing, he had condemned me to months of torment. “What then did you do?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He looked in vague pain all round the top of the room and drew his breath, two or three times over, as if with difficulty. He might have been standing at the bottom of the sea and raising his eyes to some faint green twilight. “Well—I said things.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Only that?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“They thought it was enough!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“To turn you out for?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">Never, truly, had a person “turned out” shown so little to explain it as this little person! He appeared to weigh my question, but in a manner quite detatched and almost helpless. “Well, I suppose I oughtn’t.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“But to whom did you say them?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He evidently tried to remember, but it dropped—he had lost it. “I don’t know!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He almost smiled at me in the desolation of his surrender, which was indeed practically, by this time, so complete that I ought to have left it there. But I was infatuated—I was blind with success, though even then the very effect that was to have brought him so much nearer was already that of added separation. “Was it to every one?” I asked.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“No; it was only to—” But he gave a sick little headshake. “I don’t remember their names.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Were they then so many?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“No—only a few. Those I liked.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">Those he liked? I seemed to float not into clearness, but into a darker obscure, and within a minute there had come to me out of my very pity the appalling alarm of his being perhaps innocent. It was for the instant confounding and bottomless, for if he <emph rend="italic">were</emph> innocent, what then on earth was <emph rend="italic">I</emph>? Paralyzed, while it lasted, by the mere brush of the question, I let him go a little, so that, with a deep-drawn sigh, he turned away from me again; which, as he faced toward the clear window, I suffered, feeling that I had nothing now there to keep him from. “And did they repeat what you said?” I went on after a moment.</p>
               <p rend="indent">He was now at some distance from me, still breathing hard and again with the air, though now without anger for it, of being confined against his will. Once more, as he had done before, he looked up at the dim day, as if, of what had hitherto sustained him, nothing was left but an unspeakable anxiety. “Oh yes,” he nevertheless replied—“they must have repeated them. To those <emph rend="italic">they</emph> liked,” he added.</p>
               <p rend="indent">There was, somehow, less of it than I had expected; but I turned it over. “And these things came round—?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“To the masters? Oh yes!” he answered very simply. “But I didn’t know they’d tell.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“The masters? They didn’t—they’ve never told. That’s why I ask you.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">He turned to me again his little beautiful fevered face. “Yes, it was too bad.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Too bad?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“What I suppose I sometimes said. To write home.”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I can’t name the exquisite pathos of the contradiction given to such a speech by such a speaker; I only know that the next instant I heard myself throw off with homely force: “Stuff and nonsense!” But the next after that I must have sounded stern enough. “What <emph rend="italic">were</emph> these things?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">My sternness was all for his judge, his executioner; yet it made him avert himself again, and that movement made <emph rend="italic">me</emph>, with a single bound and an irrepressible cry, spring straight upon him. For there again, against the glass, as if to blight his confession and stay his answer, was the hideous author of our woe, the white face of damnation. I felt a sick swim at the drop of my victory and all the return of my battle, so that the wildness of my veritable leap only served as a huge betrayal. I saw him, from the midst of my act, meet it with a divination, and on the perception that even now he only guessed, and that the window was still to his own eyes free, I let the impulse flame up to convert this climax of his dismay into the very proof of his liberation. “No more, no more, no more!” I shrieked, as I tried to press him against me, to my visitant.</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Is she <emph rend="italic">here?</emph>” Miles panted as he caught with his sealed eyes the direction of my words. Then as his strange “she” staggered me and, with a gasp, I echoed it, “Miss Jessel, Miss Jessel!” he with a sudden fury gave me back.</p>
               <p rend="indent">I seized, stupefied, his supposition—some sequel to what we had done to Flora; but this made me only want to show him that it was better still than that. “It’s not Miss Jessel! But it’s at the window—straight before us. It’s <emph rend="italic">there</emph>—the coward horror, there for the last time!”</p>
               <p rend="indent">At this, after a second in which his head made the movement of a baffled dog’s on a scent and then gave a frantic little shake for air and light, he was at me in a white rage, bewildered, glar<lb  break="no" rend="hyphenBefore"/>
               <pb n="18" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-18"/>
               ing vainly over the place and missing wholly, though it now, to my sense, filled the room like the taste of poison, the wide, overwhelming presence. “It’s <emph rend="italic">he?</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">I was so determined to have all my proof that I flashed into ice to challenge him. “Whom do you mean by ‘he’?”</p>
               <p rend="indent">“Peter Quint—you devil!” His face gave again, round the room, its convulsed supplication. “<emph rend="italic">Where?</emph>”</p>
               <p rend="indent">They are in my ears still, his supreme surrender of the name and his tribute to my devotion. “What does he matter now, my own?—what will he <emph rend="italic">ever</emph> matter? <emph rend="italic">I</emph> have you,” I launched at the beast, “but <emph rend="italic">he</emph> has lost you forever!” Then, for the demonstration of my triumph, “There, <emph rend="italic">there!</emph>” I said to Miles.</p>
               <p rend="indent">But he had already jerked straight round, stared, glared again, and seen but the quiet day. With the stroke of the loss I was so proud of he uttered the cry of a creature hurled over an abyss, and the grasp with which I recovered him might have been that of catching him in his fall. I caught him, yes, I held him—it may be imagined with what a passion; but at the end of a minute I began to feel what it truly was that I held. We were alone with the quiet day, and his little heart, dispossessed, had stopped.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer><hi rend="center caps">The End</hi></trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
           <head rend="center caps">Spain’s Vulnerable Seaports</head>
            <p>Should the disagreements of Spain and the United States cause an American fleet to attack the Spanish seacoast, nothing except an alliance with some European power or the massing of Spain’s naval force could prevent the ruin of many Spanish cities.</p>
            <p rend="indent">A century ago the Spanish cities on tide water were the best fortified in the world, many of them being almost impregnable. To-day the only town on the Spanish coast which could not be destroyed by the guns of our fleet is Gibraltar, an English possession. Thanks to the friendly feeling of the English, the Stars and Stripes can pass by the great rock unmolested, as its guns completely command the entrance to the Mediterranean.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Three of Spain’s seaports outside of Gibraltar would be at our mercy. On the Bay of Biscay, within six miles of the open sea, are the cities of Santander and Corunna. They are of about the same size, each having a population of thirty-five thousand. From them are shipped large quantities of iron and copper ore, and at Santander is a large portion of Spain’s wheat supply from abroad. Although a battery was placed on Santander Bay about two years ago, its guns are very light and would not prevent such cruisers as the <name rend="italic">Brooklyn</name> and <name rend="italic">Minneapolis</name> from steaming to within three miles of the heart of the city. Corunna, containing an obsolete citadel and two small forts, is practically in the same condition and could be destroyed by shells from any modern vessel.</p>
            <p rend="indent">A far more important port, however, is Cadiz, on the Atlantic coast, northwest of Gibraltar. This is one of the oldest and wealthiest cities of Europe. It is at the end of a narrow peninsula and surrounded by walls built several centuries ago. The harbor is so good that vessels drawing thirty feet of water can approach within pistol shot of the docks. The only protection against an attack from sea is a chain of sunken rocks about two miles from shore; there is nothing, however, to prevent a warship’s 8-inch guns from reducing its principal buildings to ashes. Cadiz is one of Spain’s largest naval stations and contains a dry dock and several extensive shipyards, all of which are within easy range of modern ordnance, while the extent of coast-line is such that it would be impossible to place any chain of torpedoes or other submarine defenses in such a manner as to prevent an enemy from coming within attacking distance.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The Mediterranean coast of Spain is still more vulnerable; it is also more important, owing to the number and size of its seaports. From the border of France westward to Gibraltar are to be found harbors large and small upon which are towns of importance. Beginning at the east with Barcelona, Spain’s largest seaport city, and ending at Malaga on the west, a series of seven important cities are located directly on the coast or within five miles of it. Besides those mentioned are Tarragona, Valencia, Alicante, Cartagena and Almeria. Barcelona is the great industrial city of the country, the majority of its population being engaged in the manufacture of cotton, woolen and silk goods, and ornamental glass. Here the government manufactures cannon, small-arms, and powder. The harbor contains twenty feet of water in the shallowest part and is crowded with shipping. Every portion of the anchorage would be within range of the 8 and 10-inch rifles of cruisers at the harbor’s mouth. The trade of Barcelona has been estimated at $25,000,000 annually, and its people are among the wealthiest in Spain.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Further westward is Tarragona, which, like Valencia, Alicante and Malaga, is the center of an extensive grape growing district. Its population is about twenty-seven thousand. Within half a day’s run by sea to the west is the famous town of Valencia, located on the Guadalquivir River, four miles from the sea. Its factories have made it one of the richest cities of Europe, its specialties being silk and linen fabrics, wine, fruit and raisins. Olive oil and wines are shipped in large quanitites from Alicante.</p>
            <p rend="indent">From the American standpoint Cartagena may be considered the most important of Spanish cities. Here are the largest arsenals, and an ordnance factory which for hundreds of years has turned out most of the cannon used by the Spanish forces. The guns of the famous Armada of Philip II. were made at this port in buildings the ruins of which are still to be seen: Cartagena’s sail-makers supplied the canvas for all the Spanish vessels which took part in the great sea-fights of history. The Spanish naval officers receive their education at the school of Cartagena, which may be termed the Annapolis of Spain. Of the city’s entire population of seventy thousand, fully one half are in the service of the government. The largest dry-dock on the Mediterranean Sea is at this point; it was built for government use exclusively.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Almeria, a city of forty thousand people, is perhaps the least important of the chain of cities, as its business is confined almost entirely to wines and fruits. About seventy miles east of Gibraltar the city of Malaga lies close to the seacoast on a level plain, nearly surrounded by mountains: vessels drawing twentyfive feet of water can readily enter its harbor. Annually it ships millions of dollars’ worth of the well-known Malaga grapes and has the largest sugar factory on the Continent.</p>
            <p rend="indent">As a traveler approaches these cities from the water, the view is picturesque in the extreme. Most of them were so placed, in the olden days, that a small garrison could withstand an army. All of them are fortified in some manner. Several are what were classed, in the old system of fortification, as “walled cities,” the most important portion of the town being surrounded by walls of masonry ranging from three or four to twelve feet in thickness. As a rule these walls are strengthened by towers or bastions at intervals of a few hundred feet, while in the most commanding position is built a citadel or fortress, circular in shape, through which can be seen the muzzles of fifty to one hundred cannon. To the novice in modern warfare the first view of one of these coast cities is imposing, for an impression of massiveness and strength is given. On close examination, however, it is seen that appearances have been deceptive. The cement has crumbled from between the great stones, and portions of the walls have fallen away, leaving gaps through which a pair of horses could be driven. ‘The massive iron gates, some of them erected four and five hundred years ago, have rusted on their hinges so that they can scarcely be closed; some have fallen down. The citadels, which are relied upon for the greatest resistance, are as a rule in a dilapidated condition, and few of them contain anything but muzzle-loading cannon. These have about the same range as the old Rodman guns with which Fortress Monroe and New York harbor were equipped during the Civil War. The strongest works are at Cadiz and Cartagena, where modern rifled cannon have been placed in the fortresses, and at Barcelona, where a pier in the harbor has modern ordnance. This includes a few Krupps, but the majority of the guns are of Spanish make. They would be more formidable in modern defenses, but owing to their elevated positions the fortresses form an excellent target for turret guns especially, which can be elevated to throw projectiles high in the air.</p>
            <p rend="indent">As already stated, the outline of the coast is such that cruisers of the <name rend="italic">Brooklyn</name> and <name rend="italic">Minneapolis</name> type could readily approach within effective distance. Most of the attacks would probably be made by the ships, for the height of the fortresses and the steep ascents to the defenses would place storming parties at great disadvantage; Cadiz, for instance, is on a hill five hundred feet above tide water, while Tarragona is divided into two parts, the “upper town,” as it is called, being seven hundred and fifty feet above the sea. Alicante is also elevated nearly three hundred feet above the landing mole. Cartagena and Malaga are the only cities on comparatively low ground.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Had the Spaniards prepared their cities for defense with modern disappearing guns, surrounded by emplacements such as America and Great Britain have been building within the last few years, the natural features of most of their cities would make them practically invincible; but they have neglected their opportunities. So, although the fortifications are being patched up here and there and a few high-power guns placed in the larger towns, as already stated, it would require several years to place them in the proper condition to withstand the attack of a modern fleet.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The wealthiest section of the kingdom lies along the southern and southwestern seacoast. Its most productive vineyards, its most fertile grain fields, and its richest pasture lands, are on the Mediterranean, and their products find a market at the seaports; consequently, should the latter be placed under ransom by an enemy, their inhabitants could raise ten times as much as their countrymen in the interior. The cities of Barcelona or Malaga could readily contribute five times the cost of the <name rend="italic">Maine</name> rather than suffer bombardment by such ships as Uncle Sam could send across the water.</p>
            <p rend="indent">It is improbable that Spain would neglect to make some show of resistance; she has old cruisers that might be utilized for coast defense purposes, especially to prevent landings of troops, but the range of naval guns is determined largely by caliber, and it is known that Spain has no surplus stock of large rifled cannon.</p>
         </div>
           <pb n="19" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-19"/>
           <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
           <pb n="20" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-20"/>
           <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
           <pb n="21" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-21"/>
           <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
           <pb n="22" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-22"/>
           <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
           <pb n="23" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-23"/>
           <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
           <pb n="24" facs="Colliers-vol21no2-24"/>
           <gap extent="1" unit="image" reason="editorial"/>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
